good evening everyone my name is Anna
ghee and I run the Ames Moot Court
Competition for the board of student
advisors
welcome to the Ames moot court final
round presiding over this year's
competition are the Honorable Sonia
Sotomayor of the Supreme Court of the
United States the Honorable Susan L
Carney of the United States Court of
Appeals for the Second Circuit and the
Honorable Jennifer Walker elrod of the
United States Court of Appeals for the
Fifth Circuit tonight's case was written
by Elizabeth bark Aspray lager and to
gender sing this evenings case poses two
key questions first whether a statute
prohibiting an individual from
possessing a firearm if he's been
convicted of a criminal offense
punishable by more than two years of
imprisonment violates the Second
Amendment and second whether a statue
prohibiting individuals from publishing
CAG files on the internet that can be
used to program a 3d printer to print a
firearm violates the free speech Clause
of the First Amendment representing the
petitioner the grace Murray hopper
memorial team max Kochel oralist erika
herrera benjamin Lewis Catherine
McCaffrey oralist Eliza McDuffie and
Jacqueline Saul Berg representing the
respondent the Clarence Earl Gideon
memorial team Jeff Adler nikka Carr
oralist
Gabrielle bells L Marlin golden oralist
Lilly Kim and Daniel Morales please
silence all phone and electronic devices
please no photos and please avoid
leading the court leaving the courtroom
during argument thank you and enjoy the
competition
[Applause]
all rise the Honorable the Chief Justice
and the associate justices of the
Supreme Court of the United States
oyez oyez oyez all persons having
business before the Honorable the
Supreme Court of the United States are
admonished to draw near and give their
attention for the court is now sitting
God saved the United States and this
honorable Court please have a seat
petitioners are you ready
madam Chief Justice and may it please
the court my name is max Kajal and on
behalf of petitioner Ian groves I will
address the First Amendment issue we
would like to reserve three minutes for
rebuttal
thank you two years ago mr. groves
created a digital design for a
single-shot plastic firearm following
instructions provided by groves that
design can be used to 3d print a set of
parts which can then be assembled into
the firearm although similar designs
have been accessible online for years
Ames is the only state in the nation to
have made it a felony to publish such
designs on the internet that law
violates the First Amendment for three
reasons first under this Court's
precedents in Bar Nicky and Free Speech
Coalition the law impermissibly targets
groves a speech to prevent third parties
criminal conduct second the law is
significantly over-inclusive because it
prevents grouse from sharing his design
with the many citizens of Ames who will
not put it to harmful uses third and
finally the law is a facially
content-based regulation of speech that
the state has not justified as actually
necessary to solve a current problem
counselor why should we our our
established precedent isn't this a new
form of technology your honor given that
it is shouldn't we be thinking about it
in a different way
your us is the first bit of technology
that I've ever seen that can direct
another machine to create an item that
could be put to dangerous use
Your Honor several points on that first
I think with respect this is an old kind
of speech it's a blueprint it's a design
foreign object the difference is that on
the user and a person now has access to
technology expensive technology that can
following the directions of giving it's
giving this technology can be used to
give a machine directions on how to
manufacture a dangerous item is very
different than any blueprint that we've
permitted in the past
those blueprints require an individual
to actually follow them assemble all of
the mechanisms necessary to put them
into effect it's one thing to build a
building you've got to get a lot of
things to build that building here all
you need is a 3d printer essentially
we're hundred I think you need the 3d
printer I think you also need the
appropriate raw materials you also need
a significant amount of technical
know-how to know how to operate it no
doubt it's easier than building a
building but we still submit there's
quite a bit of knowledge and expertise
that goes into the downloader side
before a person can take this this file
and turn it into a working firearm in
particular your honor it's our
submission as we say in our brief that
the kind of file is that our client
wants to upload to the internet actually
cannot direct a 3d printer to do
anything at all they need to be altered
on the downloader end as we say in our
opening brief sliced before they can
actually communicate to a 3d printer and
we think that makes that make some
difference these really are nothing more
than digital versions of blueprints or
of other descriptions visual or
otherwise of objects and so we think
it's better to think of this as the
dissemination of those kinds of
blueprints and that we think under this
Court's precedents in Sorel and in
bartnick II the dissemination of that
kind of truthful information is
protected speech and the fact that it
can be used on the downloader end and
put to unlawful ends if the person so
chooses doesn't change that fact why is
it that your clients made a CAD that
students require the use of a metal part
so detectors could work on it I know
that he has a metal a slot in which a
metal part can be placed but isn't his
intent to actually facilitate the
illegal transport of a gun through
security Your Honor I don't think that's
mr. Gross's intent he did it wasn't his
intent why didn't he make a pedal piece
a necessary part of the gun Your Honor
the record is not clear on that and I'm
not sure why he didn't but he did I
think do everything an uploader of this
kind of information could do to ensure
that when it was 3d printed the firearm
would be metal detectable
because as the record reflects at the
joint appendix 18 the design includes a
hole where a metal slug can be inputted
and indeed but it has no functional use
that's right your honor but it's our
understanding that it would be difficult
I think to to require that too to make
the metal piece be used but it's our
required your honor that's one of the
less restrictive alternatives that we
that we suggest is it wouldn't that be a
violation of the First Amendment you'd
be up here arguing that we were forcing
him to speak in the way he didn't want
to speak your honor I don't think that
we would be saying that this was a sort
of sort of compelled speech situation
and you'll write that under the
principles your honor is correct and
under the principles we think resolve
this case in Ashcroft and free and
Bartnik II that it would be still going
after groves is speech because some
third person quite apart from that
speech would be using it to commit a
criminal act it's important to note here
that just as it would be a third
person's independent choice to take this
firearm once it was assembled and use it
to commit a crime it's also an
independent choice on the part of the
downloader to choose not to insert the
metal slug that grouse has instructed
people who download this firearm to do
so we think either way that this is
still going after speech because the
government is worried that some
listeners for that speech will put it to
unlawful uses and that gets to the
second core point I would like to make
about this law being significantly
over-inclusive we think this law is
really no different than regulating all
leafleting to prevent littering of
course some recipients of leaflets as
this court said in the Schneider case
will put it to the littering use but
where the state retains the power to go
after littering primarily it is not
allowed to go after the leafleting even
though that would perhaps be a slightly
more effective way of advancing their
goals you could you speak to the import
of the statutes restriction on
publication to the internet other modes
of publication are made available you've
made an argument that making the schema
schematics available is important to
artistic and scientific and
entertainment serves other kind of
communicative values but your client has
available to him
their means of publication that is
offline sharing and just less broad and
perhaps unobservable ways of serving
those other purposes while mitigating
the risk that would be created by
Internet publication Wyson this is just
a kind of time place and manner
restriction that's tolerable in the
study circumstances sure your honor two
points on that first and foremost we do
not submit it's it's properly analyzed
as a time place manner restriction
because it's our submission that it's a
facially content-based regulation of the
speech and as this court said precisely
on point in the reno case if it is a
content-based regulation of speech than
even regulating various modalities of
internet communication as the court said
is not permissible because time place
manner analysis is not permissible for
facially content-based regulations but
your honor brings up an important point
about the use of the internet here and I
think the one piece of communication
that really can't be achieved by not
being able to share this with all the
citizens of Ames who will put it to
lawful and valuable uses is that the
Internet as this court said in Reno is a
more powerful soapbox than ever before
and as this court said in packing ham
just just two terms ago is is the
probably the most important way now that
citizens share information with each
other both to speak and to listen does
this statute prevents you from putting
up a website that would say that you
would send this to anyone who wants it
and then sending it in a drive to
somebody this does that is that
prohibited Your Honor I think that's
probably not prohibited I think
certainly I don't think the state thinks
that would be prohibited and since
that's what they argue and I don't think
that would be making the file itself
available on the internet which i think
is what the statute requires I'm sorry
why wait on a website you list that you
have this CAD program if you want to ask
us first tell us who you are right and
your honor our submission would be if we
understand the statute correctly that's
not covered by the statute exactly so
why isn't that an adequate alternative
why it's not being barred
website at all well first I think it's
the adequate alternatives analysis would
only matter if this law were evaluated
under intermediate scrutiny rather than
strict scrutiny we should which we
submit it should not be but second I
think there is still something quite
different well this is not quite speech
its speech that acts so why should it be
subject to strict scrutiny well your
honor our it's our submission that it is
speech and it's protected speech because
the Act criminalized by the statute is
not the use of this file or directing a
3d printer to do anything
it's the publication the dissemination
of this design of this blueprint from
person to person using the Internet as a
medium and we submit just as this court
said in Bartnik II and in Sorrell it
strongly suggested that when a person
has information especially truthful
information and is prevented from
disseminating it as they see fit that's
a restriction on their right to speak
are you saying this is a purse a prior
restraint on speech Your Honor we don't
evaluate it under a prior restraint
approach because unlike the the use of
the export regulations and the defense
distributed case this simply imposes a
quite severe criminal penalty so that's
after the fact you're not enjoined in
any way there hasn't been an injunction
and we don't think the statute provides
for that no but we still think just like
the use of the the ITAR law in the
defence distributed case this is a
content-based regulation of speech and
should thus be subject to strict
scrutiny
well these only been around for a long
time and maybe that's you I think you
think that's a plus but have any courts
grappled with these issues Your Honor
the defense distributed litigation in
the Fifth Circuit I think did grapple
with it but the district court there
really didn't analyze the First
Amendment issue very much at all they
because it was a prior restraint and
because the plaintiffs there were
seeking an injunction the court really
focuses an analysis on the preliminary
injunction factors and really ended up
saying that at least in that case the
United States government's interest in
preventing the dissemination of those
files overseas really overcame any
analysis here but really it's a quite
different case here precisely because
the rights to receive this information
of citizens and aims are also being
violated by this law and this Court has
said consistently that the First
Amendment protects not just the rights
of speech
but also of listeners and this gets back
to justice carnies question about the
use of the Internet we think preventing
the dissemination of this information
over the Internet
really does burden heavily the Rights of
Persons and aims who are going to put
this information to lawful and valuable
uses let me interrupt for just a minute
I mean is your position following up on
justice Sotomayor's question is your
position that the fact that there is a
significant functional aspect to the CAD
files that are downloadable albeit with
additional expertise and action by the
receiver is it your position that has no
effect on our analysis that this is
purely a content-based speech regulation
and we should overlook the technological
aspects of the information that's being
conveyed your honor right I think that
is our submission and for two important
reasons I think it would be a mistake to
follow the Corley court and other courts
that considered speech the courts the
state the state addresses in their brief
and diminished the protection of this
speech exempt it from the normal
presumption against the
constitutionality of content-based
restrictions we think that would be the
case for two reasons first Reid made
very clear that the before we get to the
government's purpose in looking at
whether a law is content-based or
content neutral we first have to ask
whether it is facially content-based on
its face or not and we submit this law
is facially content-based on its face
quite clearly it only prescribes
publication of this information if it
describes a certain kind of firearm so
that's clearly facially content-based
but again regardless of its functional
purpose so if it were a recipe to create
some toxic drug it's still a recipe no
more than that and they should overlook
the other aspects and the state is
misguided than in your view in pointing
out that the ready availability of this
recipe could undermine its whole gun
regulation scheme for in terms of
tracking guns and so on your honor it
has no import at all in your view I
think that's right your honor because I
think the state's interest would be the
same if it wanted to go after the
publication of gunsmithing manuals in
books they would still have a fear that
persons would be able to as we say in
our brief order unfinished lower
receivers and all of the
the necessary parts from the internet
which they can now do completely
unregulated and assemble those firearms
I think the interest would be the same
does it matter that your clients version
is not a fully functional version that
it requires some the end-user to have
the right software to download it
properly I think it matters to the
analysis of whether or not this is
speech that's itself integral to
criminal conduct
perhaps if this firearm if this was
essentially equivalent to the
distribution of the firearm itself if
there really was no difference and no
distance between the act of uploading
this file to the internet and the and
then the downloader having a working
firearm in their hand perhaps we would
say that it is essentially the
distribution of a firearm there is a
difference because doesn't themes have a
law that you have to register any
firearm that you possess Your Honor I'm
not aware of that law if that law exists
I do not believe it does i understanding
is in a names just like under federal
law if one manufactures a firearm for
home use only then it does not need to
be registered or serialized but indeed
it's your honor raises an important
point that other states have
requirements just like that as we say in
our brief at our opening brief at page
36 the state of California has responded
to the problem of potential 3d printing
of firearms by requiring the
serialization and registration of any
firearm plastic are not manufactured at
home and it's our understanding this
just happened recently that New Jersey
is about to pass a law that would outlaw
the 3d printing of firearms altogether
now it's our submission and our third
argument is that where other
jurisdictions have seen that less speech
restrictive alternatives are effective
and work that raises a strong
presumption as this court put it in the
McCullen case that the state has formed
scuse me how do we know that they work
well your honor it raises an inference
that they work because these files have
been online for five years as we say
since Cody Wilson first put his files on
the internet they've been easily
findable the states have really seen no
problems at least with single-shot
plastic firearms and because other
jurisdictions have seen that they're
able to to achieve their interest or at
least think that they will in the last
couple of years not by going
after speech as the state of aims is
done here so we have to wait until
people are murdered your I can't
the shooter can't be traced and there's
no way of detecting who the perpetrator
is before states can take a prophylactic
measure to protect themselves Your Honor
we don't think the state has to wait for
people to be murdered it's our
submission that where we've provided
many reasons why bad actors are really
unlikely to use 3d printing as a way to
circumvent the law they have other means
at their disposal the state has
especially its strict scrutiny heavy
burden to overcome to show that it in
fact that is not the case
thank you we ask this court reverse
[Music]
you may proceed madam Chief Justice and
may it please the court my name is
Katherine McCaffrey and on behalf of
petitioner Ian groves I will address the
Second Amendment issue 15 years ago mr.
groves committed a non-violent crime
which was classified by the state of
aims as a misdemeanor and for which he
received no jail time today aim seeks to
enforce a statute that would prevent him
from possessing any type of firearm for
any purpose for the rest of his life the
statute is unconstitutional as applied
to mr. groves for two reasons first it
is a complete and permanent deprivation
of his fundamental right to bear arms
and those should be subject to per se
invalidation second at the very least
the state cannot justify the burden at
this ban imposes can I back you up a
moment there are only two states left
maybe just one that banned felons from
ever voting and we've upheld those bans
as the prerogative of the states why is
it that the mere conviction of an
individual is not a forfeiture or waiver
of entitlement to certain constitutional
rights including this one the possession
of a firearm what makes this any
different than the fundamental right to
vote we permit states to ban that
fundamental right why shouldn't we
permit the government to ban the right
to own a firearm because your honor as
this court said in Heller the scope of
the Second Amendment is set by the
original public understanding of the
right and so we need to look to practice
at the time of the founding to
understand what the original public
understanding of the right was now the
historical evidence we have uncovered
indicates that the time of the founding
an individual convicted of a crime was
only stripped of their firearm rights in
two instances when they were
incarcerated or when they were sentenced
to a crime punishable by death in both
of those instances the individual also
lost their political rights in contrast
in cases where the individual did not
lose their political rights upon
conviction they did not lose their right
to bear arms this indicate you're
showing me the
all those laws we've upheld denying
convicted felons the opportunity to vote
while they're on probation many states
have that law all of the states that had
lifetime voting bans those are
unconstitutional as well no your honor
we limit still haven't told me why you
haven't amendment is more fundamental
than those other rights it's certainly
not your honor the reason we conduct the
Second Amendment analysis in this way is
because Heller has instructed us to do
so the Second Amendment right to bear
arms was the codification of a
pre-existing right to bear arms that
existed under British common law
starting in the year 1689 and so the
founding generation was not developing
any new right they were merely codifying
a right that already existed that's part
of why the court in Heller Alfa's I'm
sorry I thought our Constitution was
creating new rights as this courts right
not to quarters soldiers was not a
British right it was codified in our
Constitution because our founding
fathers were upset that that was
happening in Britain
my apologies are on there that's
certainly right the Second Amendment
right was not at the creation of a new
right but the codification of a
pre-existing right to bear arms and it
seems at the time of the founding that
right was limited to members of the
political community Ian groves as far as
we know remains a member of the
political community and that's why he
retains his second Amendment right to
vote does your argument depend at all on
the fact that a misdemeanor that this
would have been a misdemeanor and this
would not have been a felony at the time
of the founding under any historical
understanding of his the crime that he
committed just do you make that argument
or is that not part of your argument so
your honor that's certainly relevant
that at the time of the founding
individuals convicted of misdemeanors
were not denied political rights nor
were they denied the right to possess a
firearm however even if this court
chooses not to look merely at the
historical analysis we ask this court to
confine the scope of the Second
Amendment right to the original public
understanding of the political community
and then turn and ask today who is a
member of the political community
Ian groves remained a member excuse me
an individual like Ian groves remained a
member of the political community and
thus retained his right to bear arms at
the time of the founding and he does so
today so under either analysis
Ian groves retains the second Amendment
right so just does that mean that if
your historical analysis is correct that
felons should be able to recover their
arms when they're released from prison I
think your brief pointed out that it was
only when incarcerated that they
surrendered that right so your honor
that's certainly a more difficult
question to answer what we know is that
at present the vast majority of states
limit the political rights of felons at
at least some time I think if we look at
the current political landscape the best
way to describe the felons position in
the political community is contested so
that individual may regain their right
to bear arms to say so conclusively
would require a little bit more
historical analysis do we need to look
at the political community definition in
each of the states that justice
Sotomayor was referring to as to whether
who when felons have rights to vote when
they don't so Your Honor we've put forth
the theory that the political community
is determined on a national scale
because we're not talking about any
specific case excuse me
State Constitution here we're asking
about the Federal Constitution which is
at one point in time you're asking us to
look at the founding fathers but should
we look at it in the time of the Wild
West should we look at it today should
we look at it 50 years ago how do we
decide what moment that national
consensus was founded so your honor
there's actually two moving parts to
this analysis if I may explain first is
where we set the rule for what is the
scope of the political community now the
court in Heller tells us that we need to
look to the original public
understanding of the rule the Heller
Court limited its analysis through the
end of the 1800s and so we encourage the
court to do the same today
once the scope of the Second Amendment
has been set the rule has been set as
the political community we then turn to
today today who is a member of that
political community so we're asking this
court to determine the now
no consensus today as to who retains
political rights you mean it have to do
that can you win just on a straight-up
analysis that your as-applied challenges
is good for a misdemeanor and no one's
ever made that yet it's been held by
heard by our court on that point can we
just do we have to don't do this
originalist analysis in order to rule
for your client so it's true your honor
that no excuse me none of the lower
courts besides the Third Circuit in
bender up has considered a case like
this where the individual at issue was a
misdemeanant
and in the bender up case the court
found that the law was unconstitutional
as applied to that individual this Court
does need to answer two questions the
first is whether Ian groves has the
right and the second is whether the
burden on that right is justified so to
determine who has the right we ask this
court to look to the original public
understanding of the Constitution that's
assuming we believe he was convicted of
a misdemeanor generally the definition
of felon has always been someone who can
be jailed for over a year and under the
crime he committed he could have been
jailed for more than two years far above
the minimum that most felons are
announced it's only the oddities of this
state Ames a state that makes this amis
misdemeanor so why shouldn't we use the
normal understanding of felons you're
asking us to use the original
understanding of who's a part of the
political community but you're not
asking us to do that with respect to
who's a felon two things your honor
first if this court was operating under
what was the definition of a felony or
misdemeanor at the time of the founding
Ian groves his crime forgery was
considered to be a misdemeanor at the
time of the founding now the reason that
it's important to note that Ian groves
is a misdemeanant
is because when it comes to political
rights the line between felons and
misdemeanants is actually pretty clear
now the vast majority of states only
limit political rights for felons and in
the states that do have misdemeanors
punishable by more than one year
that includes Ames but it also includes
states like South Carolina and
Pennsylvania in those states the states
only limit political rights for
individuals classified as felons what
this tells us is that the classification
of the offense is dispositive when it
comes to political rights if I could ask
in your briefs you describe mr. groves
as they never incarcerated nonviolent
misdemeanant our conversation right now
has been focusing on whether he's a
misdemeanant
or a felon but I wondered whether how
the other two aspects of his prior
convictions play into the rule that you
would propose this is an as-applied
challenge and you know you have a
persuasive argument that he poses very
little risk but I wondered you know we
have struggled in defining what is a
violent crime or a non-violent crime
what might be just looking at elements
is purse-snatching for example a violent
crime that would disqualify someone and
I wonder what rule you would propose
that we be adopting if we were to take
your general position with regard to mr.
groves sure your honor
so first just to clarify the reason that
we discussed the relative dangerousness
of the category of individuals never
incarcerated nonviolent misdemeanants is
because we didn't want to focus our
analysis specifically on mr. groves
because we didn't want to convey to this
court that we were asking for perfect
tailoring that's concededly not the
analysis here the state must only show
narrow tailoring
however we put forth that because never
incarcerated nonviolent misdemeanants as
a class pose no heightened risk of gun
violence or they certainly don't pose a
heightened risk for life that shows that
this law is not just slightly over broad
but that it's dramatically over broad
but I'm sorry what difference does it
make whether it's a felon violent or
nonviolent in your theory of this case
your theory of the cases we go back to
original intent and you tell us that
back then the only people who were
deprived of a gun were felons in jail or
people who were subject to capital death
so is your theory founded on him being a
non-violent miscreant I don't quite
understand what's the purpose
where are you asking us to draw the line
sure your honor so this analysis
involves a two separate questions the
first is whether the individual
possesses a right to bear arms that
depends on if they remember the
political community and so there is
where the classification is misdemeanor
or felony is dispositive now when we get
to the second step of the analysis so
you think three felons of any kind are
not part of the political community they
may not be your honor as I was
discussing with justice Carney and that
question is a little bit more difficult
to answer because the vast majority of
states 48 to be exact a strip political
rights from felons though many do give
these political rights back so it's a
little bit more difficult of a question
to answer than in the case of an
individual classified as a misdemeanant
the vast majority of states do not strip
any political rights from these
individuals but there's two questions
before this court and I'd like to make
that clear the first is the historical
question which answers whether Ian Gross
has a second Amendment right but the
second is the question of whether the
burden imposed by that right is
justified now to begin because this law
is a permanent deprivation of the right
to bear arms we argue that it should be
held to be per se unconstitutional but
even if this court were to proceed
through a scrutiny analysis the law
still can't pass scrutiny because the
state has failed to put forth sufficient
evidence to indicate that this that
excuse me that depriving an individual
like Ian groves is necessary in any way
to prevent gun violence now the state
relies on two studies to come to its
conclusion but we urge his court not to
rely on those two studies too heavily
that's because these studies focus their
analysis mainly on prisoners within the
first few years of their convictions but
in contrast Ian groves was never
sentenced to incarceration and his crime
was over 15 years ago so those groups
are just too different and even if in
the abstract it were reasonable for the
court to come to excuse me for the state
to come to the conclusion that it did in
light of the evidence that we've put
forth that suggests an individual like
Ian groves never poses an increase
excuse me
never poses an increase
risk of violence or certainly doesn't
after a term of seven to ten years we
argued that the state's conclusion is
just not a reasonable conclusion drawed
from such so what a reasonable time
limit to bar him under your theory here
you make a great deal of the fact that
it was a non-violent conviction and he
has not been a reservist for fifteen
years says five enough it's chann enough
is what's enough so based on the
consensus of recent social science it
seems to be that after a period of ten
years the relative risk of an offender a
non-violent offender decreases to the
point that it meets the relative risk of
a non offender and essentially the
individual poses no risk at all now this
is this is also we can also find support
for this in the practices of the US
Sentencing Commission which holds that
after ten years an individual's prior
conviction should not be considered in
calculating a criminal history so are
you asking us to use a ten year period
to bar misdemeanors and people who
commit misdemeanors from having firearms
is that your is that what you're
advocating here today at the very least
your honor we also put forth evidence I
thought you said it was per se
unconstitutional yes your so which is it
your honor a lifetime permanent and
complete deprivation of the fundamental
right to bear arms is per se
unconstitutional a firearms restriction
that is limited in time or limited in
scope in some way may be constitutional
if the state can show that it is
justified now it's our contention that
an individual like Ian groves never
posed a heightened risk of gun violence
and so if I love showing does the state
have to make so your honor that depends
on the level of scrutiny that this court
chooses to analyze this law under we get
districts if we're strict scrutiny
because we're out of her save and what
level of showing so what the state needs
to show is that it was a reasonable
inference based on substantial evidence
the problem with the state's evidence is
that there's simply not enough for there
to be under any definition of the term
substantial evidence to indicate an
individual like Ian groves
poses a heightened risk that's why the
state can't succeed under either strict
or intermediate scrutiny but I like it's
not
that people who have not been recidivist
for 15 years that all of them fail to
commit a crime it's just that the
numbers are small so why should we upset
the state's judgment that even a small
number of potential recidivist is enough
to justify a lifetime ban because your
honor the second Amendment right to bear
arms as this Court has said is a
fundamental right and and no amount of
justification put forth by the state can
justify the total stripping of that
fundamental right that's why we ask that
this court reverse thank you respondents
thank you madam Chief Justice and may it
please the court my name is Marlon
golden and I represent the state of Ames
I will show that the Ames felon in
possession law does not offend the
Second Amendment
my co-counsel Nick Carr will show the 3d
printed gun violence prevention act does
not violate the First Amendment we ask
the court to affirm on both counts the
right to bear arms does not extend a
person's our society has long thought
too dangerous to carry lethal weapons
when he committed his crimes
petitioner forfeited the Second
Amendment guarantee and even if the
Second Amendment protects a right to
bear arms the petitioner enjoys he has
not shown that the law as
unconstitutional as applied to him at
the founding would have been found too
dangerous we believe so justice Elrod
under what theory he would be considered
an unvirtuous citizen at the founding
your honor because he would have
committed crimes that represent severe
maladjustment and disrespect for the law
forgery would have been considered it
would have stripped him is under the
founding you have some authority for
that just justice or odd that's correct
we believe that the founding level
sources show that the number of felonies
even before the felonies had made their
way from English common law to the
United States had already balloon so we
have information that shows that even
Blackstone and his commentaries in law
of England said that there were at least
160 felonies at that time we believe I
think thought your adversary said that
forgery was a misdemeanor at the
founding well chief justice Sotomayor
even if that were so that does not
resolve this case the traditional
definition of a felony is someone who is
punishable by a year imprisonment or
more and which we look to the tradition
that the understanding at the founding
she's arguing founding what do you
arguing we argue that we argue that the
traditional restrictions on felons that
is those who are punishable by at least
a year in prison or what just additional
since when what we believe at Lisa's
traditional as this court noted in
Heller
so in Heller this court said that
long-standing prohibitions not founding
era Probus so you talk about the
nineteen there
is that what you're talking about at
least dating back to the interwar period
justice Elrod but we believe history is
instructive here as well for example the
Pennsylvania Minority Report the dissent
of minority at this Pennsylvania State
ratification convention showed that the
right to bear arms could be restricted
for crimes committed or for risk of
public and injury and we believe that
understanding is what's informative here
today so it's true that the authors of
one state what other documents can you
point to to show us how other states
responded Chief Justice Emily or that
was one state it was shared however by
the drafters in Massachusetts in New
Hampshire all of those states were
penned by anti-federalists who
eventually want out with the
ratification of the Bill of Rights
itself so it's their understanding of
the Second Amendment that the right is
not unlimited that Heller identified it
said that the scope of the right did not
extend to those long-standing
prohibitions that were understood to be
outside the scope of the right entirely
now Heller tells us that these are
exceptions to the Second Amendment right
well Hilary knowledge is a presumption
but doesn't really articulate at any
great length um as for felonies and for
people with mental illness and
acknowledges that the list is not
exhaustive but it also recognizes a
fundamental right to bear arms which
hadn't been articulated in that way
before and I wonder how the state can
justify under intermediate scrutiny say
a lifetime ban where the right is seen
as necessary to for people to defend
themselves why should someone who has
been convicted of such a an offense as
this that didn't even merit jail time he
deprived of the right to defend his
family well justice Carney all I'll take
your question about the presumptively
lawful and the scope of the right first
which is if you read the opinion in the
Heller delivered the court in Heller
delivered and its entirety it showed
that everything hinged on the fact that
petitioner in that case dick Heller was
not disqualified from the exercise of
second Amendment rights in the first
place the court also grouped this
discussion of the long stain
prohibitions alongside its decision in
United States versus Miller and that
dates back to the 1930s where it said
that sawed-off shotguns were
presumptively categorically outside the
Second Amendment right and so even if we
believe that the presumptively lawful
language refers to a rebuttable
presumption which of course the state
contests we believe that the burden that
the petitioner in this case would have
to show is that he is in some meaningful
way different from the historically
barred class and he's failed to carry
that burden well let me follow up in
just a second you said presumptively
Roth lawful doesn't mean that it's a
rebuttable presumption I mean the state
can take whatever measures it wants with
regard to felons and denying them right
and there there's no examination that is
appropriate justice Carney that's
correct when a felon commits his crimes
and is punishable by a sentence of up to
five years in prison in this case he has
forfeited his rights toothless's
guarantee is right to bear arms to vote
to serve on a jury to seek public office
this Court has noted as much in its
decisions such as Richardson versus
Ramirez and we do not believe that the
Second Amendment right stands in any way
in contrast to those rights which as a
matter of legislative grace the states
do often permit as the petitioner in
this case argues but that is not the
same as a constitutional requirement so
what do you do with the cases that we
have to deal with people sexual
predators for example and they're barred
for a time period from their computers
but there have been cases discussing
that they cannot be barred forever from
having access to a computer why why is
that situation different well justice or
I'd I would first note that again we
believe that felons categorically
forfeit their right to bear arms so long
as they remain a felon so Heller
referred to felons in the mentally ill
in the present tense and this tells us
something important which is that so
long as someone remains a felon the
state has not violated any
constitutional right when it with holds
from him the right to possess a firearm
now when that status changed
if a state continued to bar someone from
continuing to own a firearm we believe
that we might have a closer case what
I'm sorry I'm a little confused how do
you not become a felon are you taking
their position that well you're under a
criminal sentence you're a felon but
once you leave a federal sentence you no
longer are this man served his time on
probation and he's been incident free
for 15 years I'm not quite sure what you
mean
stop being a felon she certainly should
justice Sotomayor what we mean is that
someone would have to have either their
rights restored the record expunged or
would have to receive a pardon and the
statute that aims is adopted of course
references federal law provides that
someone even with those conditions might
have is an explicit restriction imposed
upon them upon expungement or pardoned
that they still are not able to possess
a firearm and we believe a rights
restored that's a civil rights restored
we believe that's probably what that
means yes and so are you taking the
position that the petitioner in this
case didn't have his rights restored
well the record is civil rights restored
the record is silent on that she's best
I said in my or but we if we even if we
assume that his rights have been
restored in this case the political
community argument petitioner has
identified simply does not resolve felon
and possession challenges if it did it
would mean that states that allow
currently incarcerated persons to vote
such as Maine and Vermont would stand in
violation of the Second Amendment when
they prevented that person from
exercising a right to bear arms if
you're wrong about that it's a felony
and that it's truly a misdemeanor assume
arguendo it's a misdemeanor do you can
you still win we can Justice elrod no
okay can you give any example
demeanor violation suspends a
constitutional right forever well
justice eller I would believe this is a
situation analogous to the sixth
amendment context so the court has said
in Lewis that certain misdemeanors are
serious enough to trigger the jury trial
right other misdemeanors are mere petty
offenses it has chosen an objective
indicator of seriousness in those cases
and it is looked to the maximum
punishable sentence we ask the court to
follow a similar path here certain
misdemeanor crimes are so grave that
they are functionally felonies and the
states have long understood that they do
not offend the Second Amendment when
they prevent people who have committed
those crimes from owning a gun because
they are more likely to abuse a firearm
as a fact of their criminal record now
this accords with long-standing
understandings of what state
legislatures and what Congress can do
and analyzing the types of people who
are more likely to commit gun violence
in the future the court said in Heller
that certain policy choices were taken
off the table it also said at the
conclusion of its opinion that this did
not leave the states powerless to combat
the problem of gun violence in this
country and so felon in possession laws
like the one that Ames has enacted is
valid policy choice exercised by the
states and all of its applications so
you're using it as a use in the status
of felon as a proxy for dangerousness
and yet not taking into account the
lapse of time the non violent nature of
the offense the fact that no time was
served and or in no time was included in
the sentence it seems like a very
imperfect match doesn't the state have
an obligation in light of the
fundamental fundamental nature of the
right to do better tailoring well
justice Carney of two answers there
first is that the unvirtuous citizen
rationale that has long animated gun
safety laws is not limited to a showing
of future dangerousness now if it were
so the statute in this case 922 G would
not include people like those who've
renounce their citizenship for example
so second if we assume how
for that the showing of future
dangerousness is what justifies Ames's
felon in possession law and nothing else
then the state can succeed if it burdens
a right petitioner enjoys under
intermediate scrutiny but aren't you
using the status of being a felon as a
proxy for dangerousness I thought that's
what I was just hearing you argue we do
believe that there's significant
correlation there Justice Carney we
believe that the legislators do not err
when they believe that those who
committed crimes in the past and have a
track record for violating the law are
more likely to violate the law in the
future and do so in a way that offends
public safety and community security and
so as applied to mr. groves who
committed a misdemeanor of forging a an
ID 17 years ago and has been law abiding
since then I think your adversary would
say that doesn't predict violence of any
type how can you can test that well we
disagreed there your honor and the
reason that we disagree is because the
court would have to require a more
exacting standard in order to struck
strike down the state's law it does not
need to show that as applied to an
individual person who is a state law
misdemeanor that the law passes
intermediate scrutiny rather it only
needs to show that the law is valid as
applied to that class of persons that
the state reasonably believes posed a
future increased risk of harm to others
is it only to gun regulation of felons
that we apply intermediate scrutiny or
is it your position that all regulation
of firearms is subject to strict
scrutiny chief justice Sotomayor of
course there are only a handful of cases
dealing with the Second Amendment
explicitly at the Supreme Court now the
courts of appeals have applied
intermediate scrutiny to any number of
restrictions on the right to bear arms
we only however proceed to strict
scrutiny if the right that is restricted
by the law is at the core of the Second
Amendment right now felons as a class
can never sit at the core of the second
Amendment right because they have
forfeited the right to bear arms
entirely
second even if we assume that
presumptively lawful means that we have
a rebuttable presumption here that
language in the court's opinion in
Heller must be given some weight and it
can't be squared with strict scrutiny
but usually means something can actually
but it so what in your judgment would
that be well chief justice Sotomayor the
rebuttable presumption if as-applied
challenges are allowed would come in
those close cases where we're unsure
whether someone can validly still be
considered a felon so for example in the
only Circuit Court of Appeals to ever
uphold a as-applied challenge to an
individual felon the person and the
challengers in that case had already
seat received relief under state law in
state court but nevertheless was still
subject to the federal prohibition so we
can imagine the opposite being true as
well now we can also imagine cases where
someone has received their civil rights
restored or received a pardon had the
record expunged by a court but
nevertheless under the statute is still
prohibited from owning a firearm and
while we still believe that law likely
could pass for name we believe that
would be a closer case and that would be
the kind of as-applied challenge the
court would accept because it would be
answering a key question is this person
still a felon
in this case there's no doubt petitioner
status has not changed and if and until
that changes the state of aims does not
stand in violation of the Second
Amendment and enforcing its felon in
possession law against several now some
have some have criticized this approach
that you're discussing this intermediate
approach is treating the Second
Amendment as a second class right would
you agree that a publisher who was
convicted of a misdemeanor could not
have his publication rights suspended
for the rest of his life
justice aura we have we have two answers
there first is that we don't advise
intermediate scrutiny I'm not the first
person to ask that question certainly we
don't believe intermediate scrutiny is
necessary here we believe that text
history and tradition of the sex
definitively resolve this question
felons categorically lie outside the
scope of the Second Amendment now to
answer your question about the publisher
in the First Amendment question I would
need to say that the rights proceed from
different historical rationales so
whereas someone who is prohibited from
engaging in the marketplace of ideas has
had a disability worked upon him to
engage in the fundamental right of
freedom of expression someone who is
violated by a statute that prohibits
someone when he belongs to a class that
is shown to be more dangerous that is a
simple exercise of the state police
power it is justified not as a punitive
measure against him but by a exercise of
the state's ability to protect public
safety so you're saying we are supposed
to treat the first and second
differently is that what you're saying
just justice Elrod we believe that the
Second Amendment guarantee is just as
fundamental as the first we only say
that different purposes animate a felon
in possession law as opposed to those
that would hypo was a misdemeanor even a
state law misdemeanor that might be
subject to a traditional felon in
possession law because of the virtue of
the number of years that he can be
placed in a term of years in prison so
if we understand that the long-standing
tradition of felon in possession laws
that this court said was lawful in
Heller remains just as lawful today the
only reason that the court could find
for the petitioner is if he was able to
distinguish himself from the mine-run of
cases that challenged felon in
possession laws in this country year in
and year out and that is a burden that
petitioner has failed to carry in this
case even the best typos you could make
on that what's he missing justice Elrod
what's missing is a change in his status
as a felon other than him not being
convicted is that that's the only thing
missing and we believe that that is the
key thing that is absent from this case
justice Elrod if there are no further
questions we ask the court to affirm
thank you thank you thank you madam
Chief Justice and may it please the
court
my name is Nick akar and today I will
argue that the aims 3d printed gun
violence prevention Act is
constitutional
your honors today technology enables
individuals to 3d print guns in the
comfort of their own home publishing
these files offers individuals a new
form of gun distribution that
circumvents both state and federal gun
safety we don't permit the banning of
books but teach people how to make bombs
the books don't provide the raw
materials they don't provide the
instruments to make the bombs so they're
not much different than my mind the
diagrams so why is the fact that a CAD
diagram capable of being put into effect
by someone else any different than a
bomb-making book Your Honor we would
argue that these 3d printable gun files
those are regulated by the GV PA the Gun
Violence Prevention Act and aims are not
simple blueprints they are not the
blueprint that tells an individual how
to make a gun
they're the blueprint that actually
makes the gun this is a form of
technology that this court or any court
for that matter has ever countenance
it's a technology that can build an
object and it's in that way it's
important to understand exactly what the
GV PA regulates you see the axe plain
language limits its scope to a subset of
CAD files or computer code those that
can automatically print an operational
gun in other words your honors the GV PA
does not regulate firearm design files
or CAD files that simply depict virtual
guns it only applies to those that can
automatically create and produce an
operational firearm those that are ready
ensure that sounds nice but as I
understand it it can't you just don't
take of CAD
script put it into the computer and the
gun comes out of the computer as I
understand it you have to adjust the
program to a particular preacher you
have to change the printing mechanism to
do the slices and then you have to
provide the raw materials and all sorts
of other steps have to be taken before
the gun produces it doesn't come out of
the cat wholesale Your Honor we would
disagree with that description of the
technology it is true that individuals
might have to put the puzzle pieces of
the gun together or purchase the raw
materials but it is not true that CAD
files with ready instructions encoded
within them can be published on the
internet those files are available and
in fact a domestic abuser names just two
years ago downloaded one of these files
and there's no evidence in the record to
suggest that there was any slicing
needed and in fact well he only as I
understood it used a CAD part in a
completed gun he didn't use the whole
certainly Your Honor I it is possible
for these CAD files to print parts but
the contention here as chief justice
sotomayor you mentioned is that the
files are require a number of steps and
we would disagree with that contention
while they do require some steps there
are CAD files that unlike firearm design
files which do not have instructions to
a 3d printer there are files that do
have instructions to a 3d printer and
would enable a young child or a domestic
user or a felon to very easily print
their very own gun in the comfort of
their own home it still isn't this is a
content-based restriction this is saying
you cannot publish to the Internet
upload files that provide information
that can be accessed and read and
understood by a user albeit with a
functional aspect to it but we don't
like content-based restrictions
generally you have to satisfy strict
scrutiny and you know the record
suggested that such files and
alternative CAD programs and related
programs have been available for quite a
while
that Ames is the only jurisdiction that
is banning their uploading to the
Internet and what I need you to explain
to me why the state is a compelling
interest that is narrowly tailored in
restricting the transfer of this
information in the way that the statute
does certainly your honor I'll adjust
the first part of your question noting
that this might be a content-based
regulation and we would reject that
contention under read a content-based
regulation is content-based if it
regulates based off of the idea or the
message expressed and that's not what
the GV PA does here the gvp a regulation
says don't don't upload a diagram of a
gun how is that not an idea well your
honor under the plain text of the
statute the statute does not say that an
individual cannot upload a diagram of
the gun of a gun it simply indicates
that an individual cannot upload onto
the internet available to the public a
diagram of a gun that can automatically
produce a firearm a diagram that has
instructions that would enable somebody
to automatically print a firearm that
functional component is vitally
important to the narrow tailoring of the
GV PA to justice karna justice karna to
your point and in that way it's
important also to recognize that in
contradiction of petitioners statement
Ames is not the only state to have
prohibited the publishing of these files
New Jersey recently prohibited the
publishing of these 3d printable gun
files and for that matter over the past
five years the publishing of these files
has actually been illegal under a
nationwide injunction presented in the
defense distributed cases that has only
become illegal in August furthermore
since those files have been allowed to
be uploaded legally after the Trump
administration has allowed for them to
be uploaded over 20 states including
California Washington North Carolina and
a number a number of others who
understand that the uploading of these
3d printable gun files poses a threat to
both public safety and got any - are you
agreeing though that we have a
content-based restriction on speed
no your honor why not we don't believe
this is a content-based restriction
because it it regulates based off of the
functionality of the file but but what
the statute says is you may not publish
over the internet digital instructions
in the form of CAD files or other
computer code code is communication
files or communication digital
instructions are communication and it's
a particular kind of instruction or
communication that is regulated here I
don't understand why that is in a
content-based restriction as to which we
apply strict scrutiny well your honor in
the first instance we'd argue that this
speech if it is to be categorized as
speech by this Court should actually be
unprotected by the First Amendment
because it is integral to criminal
conduct under this course jurisprudence
in Gibbon II and thus the content-based
angry need not even come up I'm sorry
what's intricate there is no unless
there's a law and aims that you can't
possess a firearm in your home what's
illegal about having a CAD created gun
in your home your honor under Section
922 D of the Federal firearm statute
there's a restriction on the
indiscriminate distribution of guns to
individuals they cannot legally own them
there's also a restriction across not
that's certain convicted felons can't
own them yes sir a normal unconvicted
person myself sitting in my home can I
own a gun yes your honor I would presume
so if I were to take this CAD program
and create a gun
other than this law would I be breaking
any other law you would not your honor
and we believe that the G V so why is
this an instrumentality of a crime of
criminal conduct it's the person who
uses it illegally who's committing the
crime it's not the program committing
the crime well your honor we believe the
internet is important to distinguish
here because on the internet there are
proximately by our calculations about
one in every four persons are prohibited
from owning a firearm on those who have
access to the Internet and under Federal
Firearms ovulation we have one out of
four Internet users or convicted felons
I know your honor but children are also
prohibited from owning handguns those
handguns that petitioner wishes to put
freely on online and we would argue
what's the source of that statement Oh
your honor
according to recent census data there
are about 75 to 80 million children in
the u.s. who have internet access and
there are a number about 5 to 6 million
felons and that's not even counting
those citizens as whose non-citizens who
are here in the United States who cannot
own a gun so your argument is that
because there are people who are not
allowed we'll just call them bad people
or people who are too young can't have
this that the people lawful people
should be deprived access why is it that
just quintessential over breath Your
Honor we don't think that the lawful
individuals who can own this gun are
deprived of access the gvp a we'd argue
does not is not a total ban on 3d
printable gun files it allows for
private communications and as justice
Elrod you noted it even allows for a
website to be posted and information to
be disseminated to let people know that
if they want these files they can
distribute them privately but not
publicly in an area where children and
felons can download these files at a
whim if they want to and possess a 3d
printable gun well so why isn't it that
you didn't regulate that activity why a
total ban rather than one that says if
you're going to share a file you have to
have that person identify themselves
Your Honor we think in the context of
gun regulations it's important to have
both preventive and remedial measures
this court in the federal federal
firearm regulations have recognized this
not only banning the distribution of
guns generally and also not simply
requiring registration of firearms after
they're given to from a federal firearm
dealer to an individual but they put in
place a federal background
check the GV PA acts like that federal
background check in that it is a
preventative basis speech so if you
can't be you can't chill per protected
speech you have to be left to Taylor
well Your Honor we do believe that this
is narrowly tailored in that it does not
touch all firearm design files it had
touches a specific subset and if this
Court were to grant full speech
protection and thus reject the integral
to criminal conduct argument that we
submit we believe that it would it's
important for the doctrine the First
Amendment doctrine that this Court has
proffered and read that that doctrine be
adapted to deal with the intricacies of
this new technology most of them I have
is that although you're talking to me
about various needs of the state the law
is written isn't even satisfying one of
those needs because is your adversary
correct that someone can put this cat on
a website or offer it and as long as
someone privately emails them for it
they can share it we do believe that
would be allowed under the GV PA your
honor so if it allows that what is the
ban accomplishing your honor the ban is
accomplishing something that occurred
and aims just two years ago and other
other instances where individuals who
would like to have these files at a
moment's notice can get them it also
disables all that gentlemen would have
had to do was to write to the petitioner
and ask him for a copy of the CAD and
that would have been perfectly legal
your honor we think the delay here is
important in the context of gun laws the
narrow tailoring is sufficient here
because it doesn't burden substantially
more speech that is then is necessary
for example the GV PA could have been
written to cover those files without
instructions to a 3d printer but the
aims legislature decided to narrowly
tailored statute so that it wouldn't
confront the issues posed by the First
Amendment doctrine but we do argue that
the First Amendment doctrine needs to be
changed in the context of this new type
of speech if this Court were to grant
protection to 3d printable gun files so
you're saying you can delay what for 48
hours for 72 you can delay speech rights
for a certain time periods we don't
allow the delay of First Amendment
rights for time periods a or other
fundamental rights except under very
limited circumstances certainly Your
Honor this Court made that point clear
in part Nikki stated that there are some
rare occasions in which a law
suppressing one-party speech may be
justified by an interest in deterring
criminal conduct by another and we think
in the context where a file like the 3d
printable gun file that you hear can
automatically produce a firearm that is
the rare scenario that we have here and
for that reason we urge this court to do
what it did in Denver and and carpenter
and adjust its president in the face of
technology that we've never seen before
in Carpinteria this Court stated firmly
that when confronting new concerns
wrought by digital technology
this Court has strayed away from
uncritically applying its prior
precedent and for that reason we urge
this court to understand that this
speech if it is to be categorised speech
is entirely different from any type of
speech that this Court has seen before
but if this court were to move on and
not adapt its precedent in applying
intermediate scrutiny to 3d printable
gun files that are based on the
functionality of the file rather than
the idea our message is expressed we do
think that we need to have produced a
minute please
in assessing whether you've shown a that
this law is necessary given the First
Amendment concerns that my colleagues
have have raised I was struck by the
points made by your adversary about the
easy availability of 80 percent guns
that can be assembled that are basically
sold in a modular fashion and that can
be put together they wouldn't escape
metal detectors I suppose to that extent
they would be somewhat less worrisome
but are readily available at the
circumvent the state of aims
registration system altogether we need
to take that ready availability into
account in assessing the
whether you've shown that this is a
necessary regulation in your overall gun
control approach I don't believe so
justice Carney although there might be
one loophole in Ames's regulatory scheme
that does not permit the allowance of
another loophole the GV PA was enacted
to close one loophole and the aims
legislature much like the New Jersey
Legislature can if it wants closed the
80% receiver loop but but this but this
loophole has First Amendment
implications whereas the other one
doesn't and that's why I'm asking
whether there can be a closer tailoring
there certainly would be required if
this Court were to categorize 3d
printable gun files as speech a need for
closer closer tailoring and we do
believe that the GV PA meets that need
because it is unlike statutes that this
Court has recently struck down as
unconstitutional under both intermediate
and strict scrutiny for example in
packing ham this court noted that the
statute there was vague because it left
sex offenders and those subject to the
statute in purgatory not knowing whether
they could access sites like Amazon or
Facebook here the statute is clear it
cabins its language its plain text to
specific files those with instructions
that can automatically print a firearm
it also allows for alternative methods
of communication through email private
messaging and others those do you lose
if we think this is content-based no
your on each restriction no your honor
we do not assume it is content-based
how do you meet scrutiny well your honor
in the first instance if this is
facially content-based we believe the
secondary effects doctrine can be used
in order to send this regulation we
never use that doctrine outside of adult
businesses and and I'm not quite sure I
understand how we would apply it to this
situation that there is a portion of the
population that might illegally use this
gun there still a portion that won't
certainly so in the secondary effects
content
there's the existence of secondary
effects that actually insist exists that
justify a state regulation but why would
that doctrine apply here I see my time
is expired if your honor would allow I
will answer as quickly as possible we
believe the secondary effects doctrine
is applicable here although it's only
been it's only been used to uphold a
statute in the adult business concept
context it has not been captained to
that area this Court has analyzed
secondary effects under Rav and boos V
Barry and it is exactly necessary here
because the G V P is justified by crime
prevention a secondary effects aimed at
secondary effects like crime prevention
your honor for these reasons we would
urge that this court affirm the lower
court ruling thank you
petitioners you have three minutes of
rebuttal are you addressing both issues
are just your issue yes your honor I
have one point on each issue I would
like to begin with the Second Amendment
issue again before this court the state
does not really make an argument for why
the law the restriction on girls is
right to bear arms would pass strict
scrutiny and to get into intermediate
scrutiny and they rely on this notion
that Heller split the Second Amendment
right into a core and a non core but I
would like to read a brief bit of that
part of Heller at page 66 35 of that
opinion it said that the Second
Amendment is the very product of an
interest balancing by the people and
whatever else it leaves the future
evaluation
it surely evaluates above all sir pardon
me I surely elevates above all other
interests the right of law-abiding
responsible citizens to use arms and
defense of hearth and home and the state
reads this to create a sort of tear or
tranche system who anybody who's not a
law-abiding responsible citizen doesn't
have the full second Amendment right but
in context it's clear Justice Scalia
Justice Scalia was simply responding to
Justice Breyer on the question of
whether the interest of persons like
Heller could be elevated over the
state's constitutional interests so that
says nothing about whether others
interests are similarly diminished as
the state says that it should be here
and in
your adversary is making a slightly
different more nuanced argument his
argument is not that there's a tear in
constitutional rights but that the
source of the state's power comes from a
different source and that the source of
prohibiting felons from possessing
firearms comes from the police source
the First Amendment on the other hand is
not a part of the policing power it's
part of the marketplace of ideas to
which even felons participates because
they contribute and so if you view it
that way how does what remains of your
two-tier argument Your Honor I think I
would disagree that the state's argument
as to the tearing portion really looks
to that felon non felon distinction but
in either event both the state's reading
of Heller and the theory you've
articulated but runs afoul of the
principle this court articulated in
McDonald that the Second Amendment is a
fundamental right and it should not be
treated cannot be treated indeed as a
second class way turning to the First
Amendment point with my remaining time
the state again today as it did in its
papers relies on a narrowing
construction of this statute indeed it
does not defend the constitutionality of
the law beyond that interpretation and
we think that interpretation presents
its own constitutional concerns namely
it would be a real chilling concern the
state would read its statute to regulate
just some computer-aided design files
even though its text plainly
criminalizes and imposes a 5-year jail
sentence on the publication of
computer-aided design files the
regulated community here is we submit in
our reply brief understands that phrase
to be the kind of files that do need
alteration before a 3d printer can
understand them and therefore even the
state's narrowing construction raises
constitutional concerns of its own and
for these reasons we ask that the court
reverse thank you
we are will retire to delivery
[Music]
all rise please have a seat
well before we announce the winners and
I don't know what the normal protocol is
the three of us want to make a few
statements so we figured after we
announce who won the rest of you
wouldn't be interested in sticking
around I said well take advantage well
the last time I was at Ames Finals was
1991 before some of you were born I
guess and this was a bad night for me
because we lost it was a good night in
many many respects and I learned a lot
but we did not win but interestingly
enough we had three judges on our panel
we had justice Souter we had judge Taha
and we had judge Patrick Higginbotham
from the fifth circuit and the reason I
tell you this is that it was a
two-to-one split decision and judge
Patrick Higginbotham wanted it to be
known that he had voted for our team and
which was which was I was happy about
that but what I was really happy was
that in 2007 I was named to succeed
judge Patrick Higginbotham on the 5th
circuit
so I and I get to work with him still
now all the time because he's a very
active judge on our court but I tell you
that so if you lose tonight you could
replace one of us said answer and I and
I hope you do and hope you do well I
want to thank you this you you could all
do this for a living you should know
that and be proud of the work that your
team has done the briefing and the
argument superb the problem is a superb
timely problem it is certainly not moot
in the first sense of the definition and
I want to also express appreciation to
the members of the BSA who worked
tirelessly and a Vaughn Smith who was
working here back when I was here and
has observed our this school for 40
years so thank you
well I did not argue here but I was
intimidated by this room and it's nice
to be sitting on the bench as opposed to
there yet this has been so much fun the
problem was really wonderfully crafted
it had so many interesting issues and
really challenging issues for both sides
I loved reading your briefs and hearing
you tonight you were so poised and ready
to parry with us whatever we threw your
way you didn't lose a beat you responded
you didn't lean on the bench and roll
your eyes at a dumb question you just
were patient and you all did really a
fantastic job and it was really just a
pleasure to be here questioning you and
hearing the the fruits of your very hard
work overtime Harvard Law School is
doing a good job and you're doing a
really good job so congratulations to
you
it's hard enough to do these arguments
when they're real when they're not
McCourt's so you might wonder why do we
do them and we can tell you that we're
altruistic that we don't want to help
our alma mater z' and
help students I admit the truth every
time I come to one of these and I see
the extraordinary performances of the
students at these exercises it fills me
with hope about the future it shows me
that you are being trained to think and
to respond in extraordinarily loyally
professional ways and that you carry in
your hands our future in a really good
way so I come here for you to give me
hope and so it's selfish of me I really
was incredibly impressed with each and
every one of you you were prepared
you knew your case you didn't let us
rattle you you had thought through your
strategy of presentation you stuck to it
you did everything we want a
well-prepared lawyer to do thank you
the hardest part of this exercise for us
is the judging because it's always so
close it's usually a hair apart between
the two teams just like tonight and we
end up voting on little things that most
people in the audience would really
rightly call insignificant but when you
have two so evenly matched teams you got
to break the tie somehow and so we found
little things to break it on but I do
want to say that it wasn't from a lack
of superb performance by each and every
one of you having said that it was
interesting this exercise it was and
what I found so wonderful about it is
these are cases that are going to come
through the courts
they are wending their way through the
courts right now the first issue on on
these CAD designs as one of you pointed
out new jersey has a similar law and
that's already in the courts with
respect to the second issue it was one
that was raised by a cert petition if
not a year two years ago and so it's
down there percolating whether the fact
scenario that arises before us will be
identical to yours or not I don't know
but each side had stronger arguments on
one question weaker arguments on another
and it was a really well-done exercise
having said all of that please remember
that by choosing a winner of each
category it should mean nothing to the
person we haven't chosen you perform
just as well the difference was a slice
I couldn't help that best arles Matt
Scott ciao
best brief petitioner the grace Murray
hopper memorial team
and best team overall petitioner
I echo my thanks to all of the Eames
teammates who worked so hard to put this
together to all the faculty and judges
who were a part of the various stages of
the competition to all the participants
this kind of teamwork is something that
stays with you for life
judge Elrod told you her story but she's
absolutely right those who weren't
chosen tonight will be sitting in very
important positions some day and
remember her story thank you all for a
wonderful evening
you